<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Enterprise Social Network Adoption in 5 Steps, 3rd Edition</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>Alan Hamilton, Collaboration Today</orgname>
            <address>
<city/>
<street/>
<postcode/>
<country/>
            </address>
            <email>alan@collaboration.today</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <chapter>
        <title>State of the Nation</title>
        <para>The world of social collaboration at work has morphed and expanded again since the
            second edition of this book was published in August 2015.  In that there there is a
            renewed focus on discussion applications like IBM Watson Workspace, Cisco Spark, Slack
            and Microsoft Teams.  </para>
        <para>I can't readily prove this, but I am guessing the initial paradigm in social
            collaboration was that people liked to post status updates to applications like Facebook
            and LinkedIn, and so therefore basing social collaboration on "working out loud" was the
            most obvious way to implement a new model for business collaboration.  It has, however,
            turned out that this prediction while applicable in some small and isolated situations
            really has not prevailed.</para>
        <para>What has prevailed is the continued use of email as a communications tool and a steady
            encroachment into the collaboration space of these discussion applications.  I see a
            generational gap forming between the emailers and the chatters.  Those under the age of
            about thirty are comfortable messaging each other rather than using their smartphone for
            its primary purpose - to make phone calls.  This tendency towards messaging transferred
            to the business environment makes email look terribly old fashioned and slow.  What the
            messaging generation (those hooked on iMessage, WhatsApp, Facebook Messenger, etc.)
            expect is to have the clarity of discussion and threading they have in their personal
            lives, but at work.</para>
        <para>So, to be successful in driving new employee engagement, unlocking experiences and
            improving productivity, all of which fall under the collective banner of "building a
            better business", we must now also include the group of solutions such as IBM Watson
            Workspace, Microsoft Teams, Slack and so on.</para>
    </chapter>
</book>
